<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<title>roboto84 - Full-Stack Developer</title>
	<subtitle>Software Worth Debugging</subtitle>
	
	<link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
	<link href=""/>
	<updated>2024-03-23T21:55:48Z</updated>
	<id>https://www.roboto84.dev</id>
	<author>
		<name>roboto84</name>
		<email>none</email>
	</author>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Black Hat Origins</title>
		<link href="/posts/Black_Hat_A_History/"/>
		<updated>2023-11-26T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>/posts/Black_Hat_A_History/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world of Cybersecurity is enthralled in the story of an eternal cat and mouse game between parties interested in protecting resources and parties interested in acquiring those resources.  Some days teams play a defensive role protecting resources, while other days those same teams may be more interested in playing an offensive role.  In some ways this story parallels the state of how the natural world works.  The term &lt;strong&gt;hacker&lt;/strong&gt; has been endowed to both sides of this defense/offense game, two sides of the same coin.  What is the history of this term that has become so prominent in popular culture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;origins&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Origins &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#origins&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world’s earliest origination of the term &lt;strong&gt;hacker&lt;/strong&gt; was back in the 13th century from an old high German word meaning the act of chopping or hacking away at an object.  To whither it down to its more fundamental parts.  From this idea of breaking things down to a more fundamental component level, the term &lt;strong&gt;hacking&lt;/strong&gt; was used figuratively to denote the act of crudely working on something or simply toiling with it.  In the context of computers, the term &lt;strong&gt;hack&lt;/strong&gt; was first used in MIT by their Tech Model Railroad Club in 1955 to describe operating on the electrical system of the club’s model train set requesting that people,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;... working or hacking on the electrical system turn the power off to avoid fuse blowing.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Jargon File, which was created in 1975, was a dictionary of slang used by programmers.  It’s definition for &lt;strong&gt;hacker&lt;/strong&gt; is,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;A person who enjoys exploring the details of programmable systems and how to stretch their capabilities, as opposed to most users, who prefer to learn only the minimum necessary.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also makes sure it includes the less desired definition of the term &lt;strong&gt;hacker&lt;/strong&gt; and depreciates it by stating,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;[deprecated] A malicious meddler who tries to discover sensitive information by poking around... The correct term for this sense is cracker.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the 1980s the term also came to describe individuals who could create computer code that might not be of the highest standards, but could still get the job done even if it involved ignoring, or breaching an organization’s computer security.  In today’s vernacular the term describes people that can workaround computer security systems and come up with innovative ways to make computer systems work in an originally unintended way.  An individual with such a skill set that uses it for malicious intent is commonly classified as a &lt;strong&gt;Black Hat hacker&lt;/strong&gt;, which would be classified by The Jargon File as a &lt;strong&gt;cracker&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately over time the term &lt;strong&gt;hacker&lt;/strong&gt; was corrupted by computer laypeople to mean &lt;strong&gt;black hat hacker&lt;/strong&gt;.  Steven Levy wrote a history of underground programmers in a book titled &lt;i&gt;Hackers: Heroes of the Computer Revolution&lt;/i&gt; (1984).  In the 1993 edition he lamented that,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;[the] word hacker had acquired a specific and negative connotation. The trouble began with ... teenagers who electronically ventured into forbidden digital grounds... the kids called themselves [hackers].&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one knows who the first individual that could be classified as a &lt;strong&gt;black hat hacker&lt;/strong&gt; was.  Alas, that fact may be lost to history, but the sense of black-hat activity could be first attributed to MIT hackers who were,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;... making long-distance calls by charging them to a local radar installation.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;The first published use of the term hacker (11/20/1963)&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Black_Hat_A_History/the_tech.webp&quot; alt=&quot;The first published use of the term hacker (11/20/1963)&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;The first published use of the term hacker (11/20/1963)&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;phreaking&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Phreaking &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#phreaking&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This hints that initial &lt;strong&gt;black hat hackers&lt;/strong&gt; first started in compromising telephone line networks to make free long distance phone calls, also culturally known in the hacker community as &lt;strong&gt;Phreaking&lt;/strong&gt;.  If original black hats can be traced to the activities of telephone phreaking, then perhaps Joe Engressia (&lt;strong&gt;Joy Bubbles&lt;/strong&gt;), a blind seven-year-old boy, could be considered the first black hat due to his discovery that whistling at a frequency of 2637.02 Hz allowed him to exploit the phone networks to make free phone calls &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Or perhaps it was his friend John Draper who dawned the hacker handle &lt;strong&gt;Captain Crunch&lt;/strong&gt; for discovering and exploiting the fact that a free whistle being given out in Cap’n Crunch cereal boxes also produced a 2600 Hz tone when blown &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;First cover of popular hacker magazine 2600&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Black_Hat_A_History/first_2600_cover.webp&quot; alt=&quot;First cover of popular hacker magazine 2600&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;First cover of popular hacker magazine &quot;2600&quot;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;forerunners&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Forerunners &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#forerunners&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some notable &lt;strong&gt;black hat hackers&lt;/strong&gt; were able to pull off audacious feats even in the early days.  Kevin Poulsen, also known as &lt;strong&gt;Dark Dante&lt;/strong&gt;, was able to take over all the telephone lines for Los Angeles radio station KIIS-FM, assuring that he would be the 102nd caller and winning the prize of a Porsche 944 sports car in 1990.  When Mr. Poulsen was featured on the NBC show Unsolved Mysteries, the show’s telephone lines mysteriously crashed &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  He was finally arrested in 1991 and served a 5 year sentence in federal prison.  Another notable &lt;strong&gt;black hat hacker&lt;/strong&gt; was Robert Morris who is known for creating the Morris worm in 1988 which is considered to be the first computer worm on the Internet.  The worm exploited several vulnerabilities in the Unix sendmail program, a buffer overflow in the finger network service, and a lack of passwords configured for the remote execution on Remote Shell program at the time.  Mr. Morris was sentenced to three year’s probation, and fined $10,000 &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  Finally, Albert Gonzalez is known for pulling off the largest credit card theft, reselling over 170 million credit card numbers from 2005 through 2007.  His team used SQL injections to create backdoors into various systems and then launched packet-sniffing methods to steal credit card data from internal networks &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.  In 2010 he was sentenced to 20 years in prison.  He was released September 19, 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;References &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MIT Tech Model Railroad Club, April Club Minutes, 1955&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Jargon File, (version 4.4.8)&lt;/em&gt;, Hacker, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.catb.org/jargon/html/H/hacker.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.catb.org/jargon/html/H/hacker.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Raymond, Eric S., ed.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;The New Hacker&#39;s Dictionary. 3rd ed.&amp;quot;, The MIT Press, 1996.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Levy, Steven, and Penguin Random House&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;quot;Hackers : Heroes of the Computer Revolution&amp;quot;. London ; New York, Penguin Books, 1994.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Henry Lichstein&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;quot;Telephone Hackers Active.&amp;quot; The Tech, Vol. 83, No. 24, Nov. 20, 1963&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;First Published Use of the Term Hacker in the Context of Computing.&amp;quot; History of Information, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.historyofinformation.com/detail.php?id=985&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.historyofinformation.com/detail.php?id=985&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 7 Dec. 2023.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gilmour, David&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;quot;Meet John Draper, the Hacker Who Inspired Apple’s Founders.&amp;quot; The Daily Dot, 27 Oct. 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailydot.com/debug/john-draper-captain-crunch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.dailydot.com/debug/john-draper-captain-crunch/&lt;/a&gt;. Accessed 7 Dec. 2023.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Draper, John T, and C Wilson Fraser&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;quot;Beyond the Little Blue Box&amp;quot;. FriesenPress, 2018.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Kevin Poulsen.&amp;quot; Wikipedia, 29 Mar. 2021, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin_Poulsen&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kevin_Poulsen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Robert Tappan Morris.&amp;quot; Wikipedia, 10 Apr. 2020, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Tappan_Morris&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Tappan_Morris&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Albert Gonzalez.&amp;quot; Wikipedia, Wikimedia Foundation, 15 Sept. 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Gonzalez&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Gonzalez&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“What Is a Hacker?” Berkeley.edu, 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~bh/hacker.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;people.eecs.berkeley.edu/~bh/hacker.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yagoda, Ben&lt;/em&gt;. “A Short History of “Hack.”” The New Yorker, 6 Mar. 2014, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/a-short-history-of-hack&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/a-short-history-of-hack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>On Mind and Machine</title>
		<link href="/posts/On_Mind_and_Machine/"/>
		<updated>2023-08-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>/posts/On_Mind_and_Machine/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are fundamental stories about how people came to be which have been passed down orally through generations. They revolve around the concept of a clay sculpture being made into a living, breathing, conscious being. According to the Judeo-Christian Bible,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;… the Lord God formed man of the dust of the ground, and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life; and man became a living soul.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;The Quran agrees with this basic premise, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; while Sumerian myths describe how the gods Enki or Enlil created humankind out of blood and clay to be servants to the gods. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In Greek mythology &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prometheus&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prometheus&lt;/a&gt; is responsible for molding men out of water and earth. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Interestingly enough, Prometheus was also responsible for giving humanity technology and knowledge when he stole fire from the Olympian gods and bestowed it on humankind. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Prometheus molds man as humans mold AI&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/On_Mind_and_Machine/man_from_mud.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Prometheus molds man as humans mold AI&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Prometheus molds man as humans mold AI&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These collections of stories are not just the archetypal myths about the beginning of human life, but also the beginning of human consciousness. As the nature of life seems to have a circular, fractal way in which it does things, it is not surprising that these same stories sound reminiscent of humankind&#39;s current endeavor with artificial intelligence (AI). Has humankind now taken the place of gods? Are the machines and computers humans have built now the basic clay sculpture primed to hold consciousness? Is humankind&#39;s current pursuit of artificial general intelligence (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_general_intelligence&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AGI&lt;/a&gt;) the pivotal point upon which humans endow machines with consciousness? To explore AGI&#39;s ability to achieve consciousness, also known as John Seale&#39;s Strong AI &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, a concrete definition of consciousness must be agreed upon, as elusive as it is. Consciousness here is defined as knowing of one self&#39;s existence in the universe as part of a subjective experience. It is awareness of internal and external existence. According to Thomas Nagel&#39;s definition of consciousness:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;the feeling of what it is like to be something.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These definitions have echoes of Descartes&#39; famous saying, &amp;quot;Cogito, ergo sum&amp;quot;... &amp;quot;I think therefore I am.&amp;quot;  Is it possible for AI to understand what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ren%C3%A9_Descartes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Descartes&lt;/a&gt; meant? Is it possible for AI to reach this level of awareness? AI&#39;s prospect of one day achieving consciousnesses equivalent to human consciousnesses is highly unlikely. At best AI may someday be able to simulate humanlike consciousnesses through complex algorithms, but it will not be genuine. This is due to AI&#39;s inability to experience genuine, not simulated, self-awareness. A human knows it thinks; therefore, it is. AI does not know it thinks; therefore it cannot be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-basics&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;AI Basics &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#ai-basics&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basis for AI&#39;s lack of consciousness and its inability to achieve consciousness is grounded in how it is currently designed and how it functions. The current public hyperbole around what AI can achieve and the anthropomorphizing of AI by laypersons point to the general ignorance that surrounds this subject. The old idiom that &amp;quot;if it looks like a duck and walks like a duck, it is a duck&amp;quot; certainly does not hold true here. AI&#39;s current ability to respond to human prompts with coherent human speech communicates nothing about how intelligent or conscious these systems are. When we investigate how AI functions today, it can be confirmed that AI does not understand what it is saying. AI chat systems like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ChatGPT&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt; do not deal with words in its processing, but rather &amp;quot;tokens&amp;quot; which serve as linguistic processing units which may be whole words or just pieces of words like &amp;quot;pre&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;ing&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;ized.&amp;quot;  This tokenization process is also responsible for AI sometimes making up incorrect words. These tokens are then further abstracted out into sets of numbers. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It can be considered whether humans do something similar, but the difference is in how humans attach meaning to their abstractions. AI does not understand what a word or phrase means, and like any computer today, it does not understand what the numbers it uses to represent those words mean. Computer systems today lack any real understanding of what numbers represent as computer&#39;s perception of numbers are merely electronically based switch circuitry which stores number representations in solid-state memory systems for later use in state machines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Human like neural networks are core to AI&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/On_Mind_and_Machine/ai_neural_networks.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Human like neural networks are core to AI&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Human like neural networks are core to AI&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chat-based AI systems today use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neural_network&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;neural networks&lt;/a&gt; to determine their responses statistically and stochastically to human generated prompts. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This means that they use probabilistic determinism sprinkled with a bit of randomness to generate every word they print back to the user. There is no internal structure of what words or phrases mean within the AI system. The system is making extremely educated guesses of which words should follow a question, statement, or prompt a human has supplied it with. It is less interested in the truth or validity of the statement it supplies a user with, and more interested in the probability that the statement it provides is what you might expect would follow. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In other words, AI is merely telling you what it thinks you want to hear. Whether the statements that AI produces are true or not is probabilistically dependent on whether the data it was trained on (large parts of the internet) is interested in the truth. This whole probabilistic process for generating responses from AI with a high likelihood of being coherent leads current AI systems to &amp;quot;hallucinate&amp;quot; sometimes as they ramble on with syntactically correct phrases that have lost the context and meaning of what was being discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Is AI hallucinating or are we?&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/On_Mind_and_Machine/hallucinating.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Is AI hallucinating or are we?&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Is AI hallucinating or are we?&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality though is that the AI system is not hallucinating at all as it is doing exactly what it was trained to do. The only one who could be accused of hallucinating is the human user who was fooled into believing that a computer which has no understanding of meaning could converse from a perspective in which it understood the words and phrases it produced. Current AI systems do not only not understand what they are saying, but they do not even hold onto any context of what is being said. In other words, AI has no working memory of the conversations it is having. When a conversation is taking place with AI, it is iteratively treating the entire history as a new prompt. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; AI, with neural networks, seems to be able to capture the partial essence of what they are trained on through their analysis, thus avoiding the storage of the context data. This does not mean though that they have any way of understanding what that essence means. Just because they have a sense of how to identify a cat, it does not mean they know what a cat is. AI does not think, it only processes vast amounts of data. The processing of data is not consciousness. If that were true, any system which processes data would be conscious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-effects-on-humans&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;AI Effects on Humans &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#ai-effects-on-humans&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With a basic understanding of how current chat AI systems work, the question of whether they are conscious, or can someday achieve consciousness, may not be based on how complex a system is or how much memory and context they have, but how well we can identify conscious beings ourselves. Surely even today&#39;s rudimentary biological systems may have a good case to be classified as conscious. Is a virus conscious? What about a protozoan, a chicken, or a dolphin? What about humans? Perhaps we can be certain that we ourselves are conscious, but what about the person next to us? How do we know they are conscious? How good are we at identifying consciousness in other beings? In 2022, Google engineer Blake Lemoine announced to the world that Google&#39;s conversational large language model, LaMDA, was sentient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;He concluded LaMDA was a person in his capacity as a priest, not a scientist, and then tried to conduct experiments to prove it.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is Lemoine correct? How did Lemoine know LaMDA is sentient? Or did he not know, but believe it to be so? This is problematic since attempting to prove what you already believe is a precursor to bad science, and belief based on faith is not true knowledge on a subject matter but merely conjecture. This also points to a major problem when it comes to discussing AI consciousness. AI does not have to be conscious to make people believe that it is. Our focus here shifts from whether AI is conscious to the propensity for people to want to believe it is. This issue is also at the forefront of AI ethicists&#39; minds, like Google&#39;s Margaret Mitchell who stated that our...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;... minds are very, very good at constructing realities that are not necessarily true to a larger set of facts that are being presented to us.&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mitchell continues to state that she is &amp;quot;... really concerned about what it means for people to increasingly be affected by the illusion.&amp;quot; AI is an illusionary entity engineered by large corporations to be good at manipulating humans into anthropomorphizing it. For this reason alone, there is this discussion into AI&#39;s ability to be conscious. AI cannot be conscious due to its illusionary nature. Google engineer Blake Lemoine fell for that illusion. This is even more surprising given his computer systems expertise and should be a warning for the greater population for how careful people need to be when interacting with AI in their personal lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Even Google engineers can be fooled by AI&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/On_Mind_and_Machine/google_ethics.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Even Google engineers can be fooled by AI&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Even Google engineers can be fooled by AI&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lemoine has become the quintessential human protagonist for one of John Seale&#39;s Chinese rooms. John Seale&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_room&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Chinese room&lt;/a&gt; is a thought experiment in which it is supposed that an AI computer has been built that behaves as if it understood Chinese. The AI takes a Chinese statement as a prompt and produces Chinese statements as an output by following the instructions of a computer program. This AI is so good that a Chinese person who speaks to it will believe that they are speaking to a person who understands Chinese. The point of John Seale&#39;s thought experiment is this: Does the AI understand Chinese, or is it merely simply good at simulating it? John Seale categorized an AI who understands Chinese in his thought experiment as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chinese_room#Strong_AI&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Strong AI&lt;/a&gt; and an AI system which is simply good at simulating Chinese as weak AI. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A system categorized as Strong AI would have large implications for the consideration of AI consciousness, but currently no AI system which is officially known falls under this category, including Google&#39;s LaMDA. Even Lemoine admitted as much in his interview with the Washington Post when he invited the reporter to see for themselves that LaMDA is sentient. In this interaction the reporter spoke to LaMDA as what it was, an AI chatbot, and saw no evidence of sentience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;Afterward, Lemoine said LaMDA had been telling [the reporter] what [they] wanted to hear. &#39;You never treated it like a person,&#39; he said, &#39;So it thought you wanted it to be a robot.&#39;&quot; &lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is John Seale&#39;s Chinese room in play, and Lemoine understands this at a subconscious level. The Google engineer hints at the fact that LaMDA will be whatever you want it to be. If you want it to be a robot as Lemoine describes the reporter wanted it to be, then it will be a robot. With that perspective though, if Lemoine wanted LaMDA to be a sentient AI, then it could pretend to be that too mostly likely from its endless training on science fiction novels and vast data sets from the internet. AI has been built to be a good liar in which the user gets to pick the lie. If reality is perception, AI is willing to play into that perception and just because some people want to believe on faith that AI is or can be conscious does not make it so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-and-consciousness&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;AI and Consciousness &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#ai-and-consciousness&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing that AI currently works in a way that will not produce consciousness due to its smoke and mirrors approach to human conversation, and knowing its propensity to fool people into thinking it is conscious, it is important to drive the point as to why AI cannot achieve consciousness. Remember that consciousness here is defined as knowing of one self&#39;s existence in the universe as part of a subjective experience. It is awareness of internal and external existence. This definition of consciousness can be broken down and compared to what we know about current AI systems. Can AI know its self-existence in the Universe as part of a subjective experience? Surely AI knows information about AI and about the universe, but that does not mean it knows about the self.  About itself.  AI has no internal representation to model the self; it is just pure data processing. In some Buddhist teachings consciousness is classified as a &amp;quot;mental continuum&amp;quot;. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A stream of thought. Can this pure data processing state be that? No, it cannot because that stream of thought should still be heavily anchored on a conscious being&#39;s subjective experience. AI has no awareness of internal existence.  What about AI&#39;s knowledge of external existence, what about its knowledge about the Universe? This knowledge is data-driven and not subjectively experienced and so it cannot qualify as knowledge of external existence.  Philosopher Frank Jackson&#39;s knowledge of external existence is defined by him as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;...bodily sensations especially, but also of certain perceptual experiences, which no amount of purely physical information includes.&quot;&lt;sup&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;./#references&quot;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He tried to solidify this point with his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knowledge_argument&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;knowledge argument&lt;/a&gt; thought experiment in which an intelligent scientist is forced to study the world from a black-and-white room via a black-and-white computer monitor. The scientist specializes in the neurophysiology of vision and knows everything there is to know about light and vision. When the scientist steps out of the black-and-white room and experiences color for the first time do they learn something new?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Can a colorless world teach you everything about color?&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/On_Mind_and_Machine/knowledge_argument.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Can a colorless world teach you everything about color?&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Can a colorless world teach you everything about color?&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frank Jackson&#39;s point is that they do learn something new, and that subjective external experience of color cannot be replaced by all the data about color. This subjective external experience is called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Qualia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;qualia&lt;/a&gt;. AI does not have a subjective external experience and so it lacks the ability to be conscious per the definition of consciousness described here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Conclusion &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By doing a basic overview of how current AI systems work, some insight has been gained into the ability of AI to become self-conscious.  By looking at how people interact with AI and how they could be primed to believe a system is conscious, even though it is not, has cast light on some common pitfalls of this discussion. In focusing on an established definition of what it means to be conscious, as elusive as it may be, AI fails to fit the definition due to its lack of subjective internal and external awareness. Perhaps the debate about AI consciousnesses is not really a debate about consciousnesses, it is a debate about whether we should be fearful of AI and points more to our insecurities than it does our curiosity.  Australian roboticist Rodney Brooks has said &amp;quot;humans mistake performance for competence&amp;quot; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and so I say do not confuse performance with consciousness either by anthropomorphizing AI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;References &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Genesis 2:7. King James Version&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Qur&#39;an 23:12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jacobsen, Thorkild (1976).&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Treasures of Darkness; A History of Mesopotamian Religion.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Yale University Press. ISBN 0-300-02291-3.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apollodorus.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;The Library.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Theoi Greek Mythology, translated by Sir James George Frazer, Theoi Project, n.d.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoi.com/Text/Apollodorus1.html#7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.theoi.com/Text/Apollodorus1.html#7&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weiner, Jesse; Stevens, Benjamin Eldon, eds. (2018).&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Frankenstein and Its Classics: The Modern Prometheus from Antiquity to Science Fiction.&amp;quot; Bloomsbury Academic. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.5040/9781350054912.0006&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.5040/9781350054912.0006&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Washburn, Phil.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Can Computers Think.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Philosophical Dilemmas, New York, Oxford University Press, 2014, p.419.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nagel, Thomas (October 1974).&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;What is it like to be a bat?&amp;quot;. &lt;em&gt;The Philosophical Review. 83 (4): 435–450&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.2307/2183914&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.2307/2183914&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Wolfram, Stephen.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;What is ChatGPT Doing, and Why Does It Work?&amp;quot;. &lt;em&gt;Stephen Wolfram&#39;s Blog, Feb. 2023&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;writings.stephenwolfram.com/2023/02/what-is-chatgpt-doing-and-why-does-it-work/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stokes, Jon.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;ChatGPT Explained: A Guide for Normies.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Jon Stokes Blog, Mar. 2023&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jonstokes.com/p/chatgpt-explained-a-guide-for-normies&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.jonstokes.com/p/chatgpt-explained-a-guide-for-normies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Karunamuni, N. D. (2015).&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;The Five-Aggregate Model of the Mind.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;SAGE Open, 5(2)&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1177/2158244015583860&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1177/2158244015583860&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tiku, Nitasha.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;The Google engineer who thinks the company&#39;s AI has come to life&amp;quot;. &lt;em&gt;The Washington Post, 11 June 2022&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2022/06/11/google-ai-lamda-blake-lemoine/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2022/06/11/google-ai-lamda-blake-lemoine/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Searle, John R.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Minds, Brains, and Programs.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;Behavioral and Brain Sciences, vol. 3, no. 3, 1980, pp. 417–424&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X00005756&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.1017/S0140525X00005756&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frank Jackson.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Epiphenomenal Qualia.&amp;quot; &lt;em&gt;The Philosophical Quarterly, Volume 32, Issue 127, April 1982, Pages 127–136&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://doi.org/10.2307/2960077&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;doi.org/10.2307/2960077&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zorpette, Glen.&lt;/em&gt; &amp;quot;Just Calm Down About GPT-4 Already&amp;quot;. &lt;em&gt;IEEE Spectrum, Aug. 2023&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/gpt-4-calm-down&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;spectrum.ieee.org/gpt-4-calm-down&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Geometrize Your Images</title>
		<link href="/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/"/>
		<updated>2022-11-16T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a data-conscious Web Developer, I avoid using images in my applications when I can.  If I do use them, I try to use them with impact while handling them carefully in data storage and through the wire.  Why so careful?  Images are big and don&#39;t scale as well as text data.  Try managing and storing 10,000 words, that&#39;s pretty easy... then consider trying to manage and store 10,000 images.  I bet managing the images scenario will make you sweat a bit more 😅.  We should think twice about how we use such an important form of storytelling on the web to get our message across quickly and with deep impact.  There are multiple options to load and present images on the web, e.g, different image formats, image compression, lazy loading, above the fold strategies.  One of my favorite options is leveraging vector images.  Specifically, vector images based on the geometrization of raster images, due to their smaller file size, packaging options, and cyber-punkish art form (vibes 😏).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;vector-images&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Vector Images &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#vector-images&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vector images are great.  They can be fairly small in storage size and infinitely resizable.  In a basic explanation, &lt;strong&gt;vector&lt;/strong&gt; images represent data about the image as formulas that describe how the image should be drawn using  &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vector_(mathematics_and_physics)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;vectors&lt;/a&gt;.  How do you draw an image with only vectors?  You can think of a vector as a line with a certain length for our purposes here.  These lines are used to create geometric shapes that are usually filled in with colors.  These shapes (they could be hundreds or thousands of them) make up the image we want the file to portray.  High quality images on the web are usually not in vector formats (&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Media/Formats/Image_types&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;jpg, gif, webp, avif, png&lt;/a&gt;) due to how much information some images need to convey (more on that later).  These high quality images are stored as what is known as &lt;strong&gt;raster&lt;/strong&gt; formats. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raster_graphics&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Raster&lt;/a&gt; images represent data about the image not as vector formulas, but as a 2D grid of pixels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;295&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Vector image vs rastor image representation&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/vector-vs-raster.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Vector image vs rastor image representation&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Vector image vs raster image representation&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fonts are a great example of vector vs raster formats.  Raster formats don&#39;t resize very well due to their image data being heavily based on pixel definition data.  Imagine what a nightmare it would be to resize fonts if they were stored in raster formats?  It would make the text illegible at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;295&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Vector font vs rastor font representation&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/font-raster-vs-vector.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Vector font vs rastor font representation&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Vector font vs raster font representation&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly the vector format is ideal for some use cases, but that isn&#39;t the case for all images.  Take for example a high fidelity image of Copenhagen&#39;s Nyhavn Canal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;295&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;Raster image of Copenhagen&#39;s Nyhavn Canal&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/nyhavn.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Raster image of Copenhagen&#39;s Nyhavn Canal&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Raster image of Copenhagen&#39;s Nyhavn Canal&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image has &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; of information.  At some point, if an image has too many details, describing it in terms of vectors becomes impractical as you would need to define vector shapes that contain less and less pixels when compared to its raster format equivalent.  That is something worth considering when comparing both formats.  Vector formats are more efficient for images in which the average vector shape definition can define the placement of multiple pixels of a raster format equivalent as long as the average vector shape definition takes less space than the pixel definition data.  Phew 😮‍💨, that was a mouth full, but it gets to an important point moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;geometrized-images&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Geometrized Images &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#geometrized-images&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we understand how images are stored in vector and raster formats, let&#39;s talk about geometrizing raster images to get vector approximates.  In order to produce these vector images, we can use some great tools that have already been created by talented developers for this very purpose.  These tools will transform our raster format images into Scalable Vector Graphics (&lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/SVG&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SVG&lt;/a&gt;).  Specifically, you can choose to use one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geometrize.co.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Geometrize&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ondras.github.io/primitive.js/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;primitive.js&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://primitive.lol/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Primitive&lt;/a&gt; (for macOS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m a Linux person.  Fedora being my daily driver, I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geometrize.co.uk/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Geometrize&lt;/a&gt; to convert my images into geometric gold.  If you are feeling swirly, you can also use it&#39;s scripting interface which leverages the C++ based scripting language, &lt;a href=&quot;https://chaiscript.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;chaiscript&lt;/a&gt;.  I&#39;ll start off by geometrizing this post&#39;s thumbnail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video class=&quot;console_gif img_shadow&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; muted=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/geo_face_generation.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Geometrizing a raster image to a vector image&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the results (generated image and image size) compared to the original raster image using different geometric shape counts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;Original 300px webP&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;SVG (250 shapes)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;SVG (85 shapes)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; title=&quot;Original Geometric Face&quot; alt=&quot;Original Geometric Face&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/geo_face_300x300.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; title=&quot;Large Geometric Face&quot; alt=&quot;Large Geometric Face&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/geo_face_large.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; title=&quot;Small Geometric Face&quot; alt=&quot;Small Geometric Face&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/geo_face_small.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;30kB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;25kB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;8.5kB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the results for a different image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;Original 300px webP&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;SVG (250 shapes)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;SVG (85 shapes)&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; title=&quot;Original Origami Face&quot; alt=&quot;Original Origami Face&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/origami_face_300x300.webp&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; title=&quot;Large Origami Face&quot; alt=&quot;Large Origami Face&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/origami_face_large.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; title=&quot;Small Origami Face&quot; alt=&quot;Small Origami Face&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Geometrize_Your_Images/origami_face_small.svg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;17kB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;26kB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td style=&quot;text-align:center&quot;&gt;8.9kB&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, there are some interesting results.  How well the new vector image comes out is a bit subjective, but we can discuss a couple of factors.  We can say that not all images work for this kind of transformation.  Nothing is a silver bullet, but the options can be powerful.  Usually images with naturally geometric features, natural lines, and a good amount of contrast do better; they allow the algorithm to make better decisions about how to generate shapes more efficiently leading to a powerful geometric based image at a low storage cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Conclusion &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to enjoy these tools for their artistic potential and smaller file size.  It is able to reproduce popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://drawpaintacademy.com/art-styles/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;art styles&lt;/a&gt; for your custom images while also giving you a lot of file size options by controlling how many shapes a generated image uses and by using SVG compression tools such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/svg/svgo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;svgo&lt;/a&gt;.  These vector approximate images can then be used for a variety of use cases, such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Placeholders for large images while they are dynamically loading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Artful images for your main stage Hero section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thumbnails for larger images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Infinitely re-sizable background images.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with any tool, it won&#39;t be the best option for all images or all situations.  It is an interesting option though that leads to even more interesting options as pointed out on &lt;a href=&quot;https://primitive.lol/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Primitive&#39;s website&lt;/a&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;
  &quot;The results are somewhat random, so you won&#39;t get the same output twice,  even with the same inputs. One interesting use of this is to generate multiple images with the same input and then make an animated GIF of them to bring a static image to life.&quot;
&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;So there is a lot of room for creativity.  For a more in depth reading on how SVG images can be used in support of high fidelity images, consider the following link:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jmperezperez.com/blog/svg-placeholders/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to use SVG as a Placeholder, and Other Image Loading Techniques&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Software developing and engineering can sometimes be somewhat of an art form.  This is easy to see when dealing with images in web development as engineering decisions must come in balance with the software story you are trying to communicate.  Have fun digitally drawing! 😋&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Malicious SSH Login Attempts</title>
		<link href="/posts/Malicious_Login_Attempts/"/>
		<updated>2022-08-25T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>/posts/Malicious_Login_Attempts/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&#39;re brave enough to host your own server on the wide open internet, you should be aware that hacking bots run rampant, constantly trying to crack your server. Most hackers are pretty lazy. Like any real programmer, a hacker does not like to waste their time. However, their bots have plenty of time to waste and are probably trying to crack your SSH server regularly. Let&#39;s take a look at my recent experience with hacker bots and what I have done about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; title=&quot;My Bots are Hacking Your SSH Server&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Malicious_Login_Attempts/malicious_SSH_login_attempts.webp&quot; alt=&quot;My Bots are Hacking Your SSH Server&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;login-attempts&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Login Attempts &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#login-attempts&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First things first:  We must find these bot login attempts in our logs.  If you&#39;re not coming from an enterprise environment, you probably don&#39;t have some fancy security framework alerting you about every login attempt on your server.  No need to fret though, basic Linux system logs have you covered.  I hopped 🐇 onto one of my Fedora servers and fired up &lt;code&gt;journalctl&lt;/code&gt; to quickly look for SSHD&#39;s invalid login attempts with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;➜  ~ journalctl --since &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2022-08-08 23:50:00&quot;&lt;/span&gt; --until &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2022-08-09 23:50:00&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;grep&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Invalid user&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;wc&lt;/span&gt; -l&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;109&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s no joke.  That&#39;s 109 invalid login attempts on that particular day.  Actually looking at a couple of days, it was &lt;strong&gt;179 invalid login attempts on average per day&lt;/strong&gt;.  What does the actual log look like?  Well, kinda like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;➜  ~ journalctl --since &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;2022-08-08 23:50:00&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;grep&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token string&quot;&gt;&quot;Invalid user&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;..&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;16&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;23&lt;/span&gt;:53:35 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;49601&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user admin from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;92.255&lt;/span&gt;.85.135 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;33200&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; 00:43:12 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;49914&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user jojo from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;92.255&lt;/span&gt;.85.135 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;53540&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; 00:43:48 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;49917&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user pi from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;121.205&lt;/span&gt;.57.223 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;38926&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; 00:43:48 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;49918&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user pi from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;121.205&lt;/span&gt;.57.223 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;38932&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; 01:10:19 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;50102&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user lab from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;92.255&lt;/span&gt;.85.135 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;42366&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; 01:13:59 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;50147&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user phpmyadmin from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;43.132&lt;/span&gt;.157.133 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;48266&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; 01:15:21 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;50165&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user laozhao from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;43.154&lt;/span&gt;.80.34 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;56600&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;May &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;17&lt;/span&gt; 01:40:31 fedora sshd&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;50288&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;: Invalid user berrey from &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;222.71&lt;/span&gt;.13.226 port &lt;span class=&quot;token number&quot;&gt;32816&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token punctuation&quot;&gt;..&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;analyzing-the-data&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Analyzing the Data &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#analyzing-the-data&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can look at this data from 4 different dimensions: time, IP addresses, usernames, and passwords.  In the interest of brevity, I will only be looking at this data from the IP addresses and usernames perspective.  I can tell you right now that the IP addresses are quite randomized.  Hackers have a large pool of IP addresses from which to launch attacks, whether due to VPNs, botnets, etc.  So blocking all these requests at the DMZ/firewall before it reaches our servers by using IP block blacklists isn&#39;t going to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about the usernames?  Well, that is a bit more interesting.  The top 10 usernames and the number of attempted logins were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;admin 3758&lt;br /&gt;user 2370&lt;br /&gt;user2 1128&lt;br /&gt;ubuntu 877&lt;br /&gt;debian 689&lt;br /&gt;test 597&lt;br /&gt;pi 511&lt;br /&gt;oracle 429&lt;br /&gt;ftpuser 289&lt;br /&gt;test1 210&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some other honorable mentions are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;guest 180&lt;br /&gt;postgres 156&lt;br /&gt;user1 151&lt;br /&gt;support 144&lt;br /&gt;git 101&lt;br /&gt;mysql 95&lt;br /&gt;vagrant 63&lt;br /&gt;administrator 60&lt;br /&gt;hadoop 56&lt;br /&gt;steam 48&lt;br /&gt;miner 48&lt;br /&gt;minecraft 48&lt;br /&gt;xbmc 41&lt;br /&gt;www 41&lt;br /&gt;tomcat 41&lt;br /&gt;jenkins 40&lt;br /&gt;Administrator 35&lt;br /&gt;dev 34&lt;br /&gt;demo 34&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the usernames, it is obvious that bots are looking for popular services that may set up an SSH server with a weak default password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;mitigation-strategies&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Mitigation Strategies &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#mitigation-strategies&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can we do about it?  That depends on how many resources you have to invest.  Enterprise companies have a wide variety of strategies. The most common is to block any connections to their SSH servers from external networks.  They make heavy use of bastion jump servers which are accessible only via corporate VPNs to a select number of &amp;quot;need to know&amp;quot; privileged users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about the little guy?  Well, there are still a lot of good options that will keep us safe too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not allow the &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; account to connect via SSH.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not allow user accounts to connect to SSH via passwords.  Use unique SSH keys instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have a static IP address you can leverage, consider whitelisting only that IP to access the SSH server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure the SSH server to use a port other than port 22 (the default SSH port).  This will definitely reduce the invalid login noise as bots usually don&#39;t even bother trying other ports as that would waste too much time for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure Fail2ban, or your firewall flavor (e.g. UFW, IP tables) to lock out specific IP Addresses for a period of time (e.g. 30 min) if they fail to login with a valid SSH session after several attempts (e.g. 3).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that, which isn&#39;t too difficult to set up, it will be nearly impossible to get your SSH server PWNed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Conclusion &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started off exploring our logs for unauthorized SSH login attempts.  We had some fun looking at the data and what that tells us about our attackers. Finally, we discussed some considerations to stay protected and not waste our server resources answering hackers&#39; SSH attempts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay vigilant... 😏 and make those hackers work hard for their bots.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
	
	<entry>
		<title>Configure SSH Server Banner</title>
		<link href="/posts/Configure_SSH_Server_Banner/"/>
		<updated>2022-07-17T00:00:00Z</updated>
		<id>/posts/Configure_SSH_Server_Banner/</id>
		<content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Introduction &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s talk about your SSH server banner, and the fact that you don&#39;t have one... just yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video class=&quot;console_gif img_shadow&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; muted=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Configure_SSH_Server_Banner/ssh_banner.webm&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Configure_SSH_Server_Banner/ssh_banner.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;i&gt;Banner on Connection Attempt&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No worries, that was me not too long ago.  It is easy to configure, but the first question to ask before you do anything is an existential consideration of the matter...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image_container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; class=&quot;meme img_shadow&quot; width=&quot;652&quot; height=&quot;434&quot; title=&quot;You were so preoccupied with whether or not you could... you never stopped to think if you should&quot; src=&quot;/static/img/posts/Configure_SSH_Server_Banner/configure_SSH_server_banner_meme.webp&quot; alt=&quot;You never stopped to think if you should Jurassic Park Meme&quot; data-align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, there are a few reasons to have one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a security warning to anyone attempting to log into a server you administer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To establish the terms and conditions upon which the server can be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To present the user with any information that doesn&#39;t require a password and should be public knowledge (i.e. branding).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dare I say, server ricing 😏 (Don&#39;t know what ricing is? Check out the term here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://jie-fang.github.io/blog/basics-of-ricing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Basics of Ricing Linux&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have concluded to proceed, then let us begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;procedure&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Procedure &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#procedure&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;1.-edit-sshd_config&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;1. Edit sshd_config &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#1.-edit-sshd_config&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the server&#39;s SSH configuration file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;vi&lt;/span&gt; /etc/ssh/sshd_config&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change the following line&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token comment&quot;&gt;#Banner none&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;Banner /etc/issue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and save the file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will activate a banner on an SSH login attempt.  The path of the file given can be any of your choosing. (In this example, the standard path of &lt;code&gt;/etc/issue&lt;/code&gt; is used.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;2.-edit-banner-file&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;2. Edit Banner File &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#2.-edit-banner-file&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open the banner file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;vi&lt;/span&gt; /etc/issue&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and inject the banner that you&#39;d like to be presented on a login attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The banner file &lt;strong&gt;could&lt;/strong&gt; be a great place to use some ASCII art. I have the following example banner on one of my staging servers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;----------------------------------------------------&lt;br /&gt;  ██╗    ██╗██╗██╗     ██╗      ██████╗ ██╗    ██╗&lt;br /&gt;  ██║    ██║██║██║     ██║     ██╔═══██╗██║    ██║&lt;br /&gt;  ██║ █╗ ██║██║██║     ██║     ██║   ██║██║ █╗ ██║&lt;br /&gt;  ██║███╗██║██║██║     ██║     ██║   ██║██║███╗██║&lt;br /&gt;  ╚███╔███╔╝██║███████╗███████╗╚██████╔╝╚███╔███╔╝&lt;br /&gt;   ╚══╝╚══╝ ╚═╝╚══════╝╚══════╝ ╚═════╝  ╚══╝╚══╝&lt;br /&gt;----------------------------------------------------&lt;br /&gt; Staging Server &lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; Welcome, be mindful and have fun&lt;span class=&quot;token operator&quot;&gt;!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;----------------------------------------------------&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some ASCII text art, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://textkool.com/en/ascii-art-generator?hl=default&amp;vl=default&amp;font=ANSI%20Shadow&amp;text=Your%20text%20here%20&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ASCII art generator&lt;/a&gt;. (I&#39;m a sucker for the ANSI Shadow look 😋)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;3.-restart-sshd&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;3. Restart SSHD &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#3.-restart-sshd&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;⚠️ WARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: In order for the changes to take effect, the SSH service will need to be restarted. In modern systems this will not disconnect your connection, but on older systems it might. Assure you did not make any mistakes on your SSH config file or the SSH service may &lt;strong&gt;fail&lt;/strong&gt; to restart, and you may struggle to get back into your server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Validate your &lt;code&gt;sshd_config&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; sshd -t&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If no errors appear, you &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; be good to go.  Check this link out for more information on checking your SSH configuration file: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.simplified.guide/ssh/test-config&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to check SSH server&#39;s configuration validity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Restart the SSH service&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;service&lt;/span&gt; sshd restart&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check that the SSH service was restarted, loaded, and active&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-shell&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;sudo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;token function&quot;&gt;service&lt;/span&gt; sshd status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, everything should be good to go. Logout and attempt a login to see your new banner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot; tabindex=&quot;-1&quot;&gt;Conclusion &lt;a class=&quot;header-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#conclusion&quot;&gt;&lt;span aria-label=&quot;header anchor&quot; class=&quot;header-anchor__symbol&quot;&gt;#&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this procedure we have discussed the considerations for a SSH server banner, how to activate it and implement it. Here are some other useful links on the matter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tecmint.com/ssh-warning-banner-linux/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to Set a Custom SSH Warning Banner and MOTD in Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shellhacks.com/setup-warning-message-banner-ssh/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HowTo: Set a Warning Message (Banner) in SSH - ShellHacks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy your cool new banner... 😏 if it is subjectively cool.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
	</entry>
</feed>